lands. Chapter 15. The gathering of the clouds.
Clouse. Now we will return to Bilbo and the dwarves. All night one of them had
watched. But when morning came, they had not heard or seen any sign of danger.
But ever more thickly the birds were gathering. Their companies came flying
from the south, and the crows that still lived about the mountain were wheeling
and crying unceasingly above. "Something strange is happening," said Thorin. "The
time is gone for the autumn wanderings, and these are birds that dwell always in
the land. There are starings and flocks of finches, and far off there are many
carrying birds as if a battle were a foot. Suddenly Bilbo pointed, "There is
that old thrush again," he cried. "He seems to have escaped when Smab smashed
the mountain side." "But I don't suppose the snails have." Sure enough, the old
thrush was there, and as Bilbo pointed, he flew towards them and perched on a
stone nearby. Then he fluttered his wings and sang. Then he cocked his head
on one side as if to listen. And again he sang, and again he listened.
I believe he is trying to tell us something, said Balon. But I cannot
follow the speech of such birds. It is very quick and difficult. Can you make it out Baggins?
Not very well, said Bilbo. As a matter of fact, he could make nothing of it at
all. But the old fellow seems very excited. I only wish he was a raven,
said Balon. I thought you did not like them. You seemed very shy of them when
we came this way before.
Those were crows and nasty, suspicious looking creatures at that, and rude as
well. You must have heard the ugly names they were calling after us. But the
ravens are different. There used to be great friendship between them and the
people of Thraar, and they often brought us secret news, and were rewarded with
such bright things as they coveted to hide in their dwellings. They live many
year, and their memories are long, and they hand on their wisdom to their
children. I knew many among the ravens of the rocks when I was a dwarf lad.
This very height was once named Ravenh Hill because there was a wise and famous
pair old Kirk and his wife that lived here above the guard chamber. But I
don't suppose that any of that ancient breed linger here now. No sooner had he
finished speaking than the old Drush gave a loud call and immediately threw
away. We may not understand him, but that old bird understands us, I am sure,
said Balin. Keep watch now and see what happens. Before long there was a
fluttering of wings, and back came the thrush, and with him came a most
decrepit old bird. He was getting blind.
He could hardly fly, and the top of his head was bald. He was an aged raven of
great size. He ellighted stiffly on the ground before them, slowly flapped his
wings, and bobbed towards Thoren. Oh, Thorin son of Thra and Balon son of
Fondon, he croked, and Bilbo could understand what he said, for he used
ordinary language and not bird speech. I am Rowax, son of Kark. Kark is dead, but
he was well known to you once. It is 100
years and three and 50 since I came out
of the egg, but I do not forget what my
father told me. Now I am the chief of the great ravens of the mountain. We are
few, but we remember still the king that was of old. Most of my people are
abroad, for there are great tidings in the south. Some are tidings of joy to
you, and some you will not think so good. Behold, the birds are gathering
back again to the mountain and to Dale from south and east and west. For word
has gone out that Smal is dead. Dead.
Dead, shouted the dwarves. Dead. Then we have been in needless fear, and the
treasure is ours. They all sprang up and began to caper about for joy.
Yes, dead, said Roach. The thrush, may his feathers never fall, saw him die,
and we may trust his words. He saw him fall in battle with the men of Esgaroth
the third knight, back from now at the rising of the moon. It was some time
before Thoren could bring the dwarves to be silent and listen to the raven's
news. At length, when he had told all the tale of the battle, he went on. So
much for joy for an oakenshield. You may go back to your halls in safety. All the
treasure is yours for the moment, but many are gathering hither beside the
birds. The news of the death of the guardian has already gone far and wide,
and the legend of the wealth of throw has not lost in the telling during many
years. Many are eager for a share of the spoil. Already a host of the elves is on
the way, and carrying birds are with them, hoping for battle and slaughter.
By the lake, men murmur that their sorrows are due to the dwarves, for they
are homeless, and many have died, and Smog has destroyed their town. They too
think to find amends from your treasure, whether you are alive or dead. Your own
wisdom must decide your course. But 13 is small remnant of the great folk of
Duran that once dwelt here, and now are scattered far.
If you will listen to my counsel, you will not trust the master of the
lakemen, but rather him that shot the dragon with his bow. Bar is he of the
race of Dale of the line of Jiren. He is
a grim man. The true we would see peace once more among dwarves in men and elves
after the long desolation. But it may cost you dearing gold. I have spoken.
Then thoren burst forth in anger. Our thanks Roakhark's son. You and your
people shall not be forgotten. But none of our gold shall thieves take or the
violent carry off while we are alive. If you would earn our thanks still more,
bring us news of any that draw near.
Also, I would beg of you, if any of you are still young and strong of wing, that
you would send messengers to our kin in the mountains of the north, both west
from here and east, and tell them of our plight. But go specially to my cousin
Dne in the Iron Hills, for he has many people well armed, and dwells nearest to
this place. Bid him hasten.
I will not say if this council be good or bad, croked Rowak, but I will do what
can be done. Then off he slowly flew.
Back now to the mountain, cried Thorin.
We have little time to lose. And little food to use, cried Bilbo, always
practical on such points. In any case, he felt that the adventure was properly
speaking over with the death of the dragon in which he was much mistaken,
and he would have given most of his share of the prophets for the peaceful
winding up of these affairs.
Back to the mountain, cried the dwarves, as if they had not heard him, so back he
had to go with them. As you have heard some of the events already, you will see
that the dwarves still had some days before them. They explored the caverns
once more and found, as they expected, that only the front gate remained open.
All the other gates, except, of course, the small secret door, had long ago been
broken and blocked by SMOG, and no sign of them remained. So now they began to
labor hard in fortifying the main entrance, and in making a new path that
led from it. Tools were to be found in plenty that the miners and cers and
builders of old had used, and at such work the dwarves were still very
skilled. As they worked, the ravens brought them constant tidings. In this
way they learned that the elven king had turned aside to the lake, and they still
had a breathing space. Better still, they heard that three of their ponies
had escaped and were wandering wild far down the banks of the running river. not
far from where the rest of their stores had been left. So while the others went
on with their work, Feelely and Keely were sent, guided by a raven, to find
the ponies and bring back all they could. They were 4 days gone, and by
that time they knew that the joined armies of the lakemen and the elves were
hurrying toward the mountain. But now their hopes were higher, for they had
food for some weeks with care, chiefly cram, of course, and they were very
tired of it. But cram is much better than nothing, and already the gate was
blocked with a wall of squared stones laid dry, but very thick and high across
the opening. There were holes in the wall through which they could see or
shoot, but no entrance. They climbed in or out with ladders, and hauled stuff up
with ropes. For the issuing of the stream they had contrived a small low
arch under the new wall. But near the entrance they had so altered the narrow
bed that a wide pull stretched from the mountain wall to the head of the fall
over which the stream went towards Dale.
Approach to the gate was now only possible without swimming along a narrow
ledge of the cliff to the right as one looked outwards from the wall. The
ponies they had brought only to the head of the steps above the old bridge, and
unloading them there, had bitten them returned to their masters, and sent them
back riderless to the south. There came a night when suddenly there were many
lights as of fires and torches away south and dale before them. "They have
come," called Baland, "and their camp is very great. They must have come into the
valley under the cover of dusk along both banks of the river." That night the
dwarves slept little. The morning was still pale when they saw a company
approaching. From behind their wall they watched them come up to the valley's
head and climb slowly up. Before long they could see that both men of the lake
armed as if for war and Elvish Bowman were among them. At length the foremost
of these climbed the tumbled rocks and appeared at the top of the falls. And
very great was their surprise to see the pool before them and the gate blocked
with a wall of new huneed stone. As they stood pointing and speaking to one
another, Thorenhailed them, "Who are you?" he called in a very loud voice
that come as if in war to the gates of Thorin, son of Thra, king under the
mountain, and what do you desire?
But they answered nothing. Some turned swiftly back, and the others, after
gazing for a while at the gate and its defenses, soon followed them. That day
the camp was moved to the east of the river, right between the arms of the
mountain. The rocks echoed then with voices and with song, as they had not
done for many a day. There was the sound, too, of elven harps and of sweet
music, and as it echoed up towards them, it seemed that the chill of the air was
warmed, and they caught faintly the fragrance of woodland flowers blossoming
in spring. Then Bilbo longed to escape from the dark fortress, and to go down
and join in the mirth, and feasting by the fires. Some of the younger dwarves
were moved in their hearts, too, and they muttered that they wished things
had fallen out otherwise, and that they might welcome such folk as friends. But
Thorin scowlled. Then the dwarfs themselves brought forth harps and
instruments regained from the horde, and made music to soften his mood, but their
song was not as elish song, and was much like the song they had sung long before
in Bilbo's little hobbit hole. Under the mountain dark and tall, the king has
come unto his hall. His foe is dead, the worm of dread, and ever so his foe shall
fall. The sword is sharp, the spear is long, the arrow swift, the gate is
strong, the heart is bold that looks on gold. The dwarves no more shall suffer
wrong. The dwarves of Yor made mighty spells, while hammers fell like ringing
bells, in places deep where dark things sleep, in hollow halls beneath the
fells. On silver necklaces they strung, the light of stars on crowns they hung.
The dragon fire from twisted wire, the melody of harps they rung. The mountain
throne once more is freed. Oh wandering folk the summons heed. Come haste, come
haste. Across the waist, the king of friend and kin has need. Now call we
over mountains cold. Come back unto the caverns old. Here at the gates the king
awaits. His hands are rich with gems and gold. The king is come unto his hall
under the mountain dark and tall. The worm of dread is slain and dead. And
ever so our foes shall fall. This song appeared to please Thorin, and he smiled
again, and grew merry, and he began reckoning the distance to the iron
hills, and how long it would be before Dne could reach the lonely mountain, if
he had set out as soon as the message reached him. But Bilbo's heart fell,
both at the song and the talk. They sounded much too warlike.
The next morning, early a company of spearmen was seen crossing the river and
marching up the valley. They bore with them the green banner of the elven king
and the blue banner of the lake, and they advanced until they stood right
before the wall at the gate. Again Thorin hailed them in a loud voice, "Who
are you that come armed for war to the gates of Thorin, son of Thra, king under
the mountain." This time he was answered. A tall man stood forward, dark
of hair and grim of face, and he cried, "Hail Thoren! Why do you fence yourself
like a robber in his hold? We are not yet foes, and we rejoice that you are
alive beyond our hope. We came expecting to find none living here. Yet now that
we are met, there is matter for a parley and a council. Who are you, and of what
would you parlay? I am barred, and by my hand was the dragon slain, and your
treasure delivered. Is that not a matter that concerns you? Moreover, I am by
right descent the heir of Jiren of Dale, and in your horde is mingled much of the
wealth of his halls and towns, which of old Smog stole. Is not that a matter of
which we may speak? Further, in his last battle, Smav destroyed the dwellings of
the men of Esgaroth, and I am yet the servant of their master. I would speak
for him, and ask whether you have no thought for the sorrow and misery of his
people. They aided you in your distress, and in recompense you have thus far
brought ruin only, though doubtless undesigned.
Now these were fair words and true, if proudly and grimly spoken, and Bilbo
thought that Thoren would at once admit what justice was in them. He did not, of
course, expect that anyone would remember that it was he who discovered
all by himself the dragon's weak spot, and that was just as well, for no one
ever did. But also he did not reckon with the power that gold has upon which
dragon has long brooded, nor with dwarfish hearts. Long hours in the past
days Thoren had spent in the treasury, and the lust of it was heavy on him.
Though he had hunted chiefly for the arkan stone, yet he had an eye for many
another wonderful thing that was lying there, about which were wounded old
memories of the labors and the sorrows of his race. You put your worst cause
last and in the chief place, Thorin answered. To the treasure of my people,
no man has a claim. Because Mau stole it from us also robbed him of life or home.
The treasure was not his that his evil deeds should be amended with a share of
it. The price of the goods and the assistance that we received of the
lakemen we will fairly pay in due time.
But nothing will we give, not even a loaf's worth under threat of force.
While an armed host lies before our doors, we look on you as foes and thieves.
It is in my mind to ask what share of their inheritance you would have paid to
our kindred had you found the horde unguarded and us slain.
A just question, replied Bard. But you are not dead, and we are not robbers.
Moreover, the wealthy may have pity beyond right on the needy that
befriended them when they were in want, and still my other claims remain unanswered.
I will not parlay, as I have said, with armed men at my gate, nor at all with
the people of the Alvin King, whom I remember with small kindness.
In this debate, they have no place. Be gone now, air, our arrows fly. And if
you would speak with me again, first dismiss the Elvish host to the woods
where it belongs, and then return, laying down your arms before you approach the threshold.
The elven king is my friend, and he has suckered the people of the lake in their
need, though they had no claim but friendship on him, answered Bard. We
will give you time to repent your words.
Gather your wisdom, air we return. Then he departed and went back to the camp.
Many hours were passed. The banner bearers returned and trumpeters stood
forth and blew a blast. In the name of Escaroth and the forest, one cried, "We
speak unto Thorenthra's son Oakenshield, calling himself the king under the
mountain, and we bid him consider well the claims that have been urged or be
declared our foe." At the least he shall deliver one 12th portion of the treasure
unto Bard as the dragon slayer and as the heir of Jiren. From that portion
Bard will himself contribute to the aid of Esgar. But if Doran would have the
friendship and honor of the lands about, as his sireers had of old, then he will
give also somewhat of his own for the comfort of the men of the lake. Then
Thoren seized a bow of horn and shot an arrow at the speaker. it smoked into his
shield and stuck there quivering.
Since such is your answer, he called in return, I declare the mountain besieged.
You shall not depart from it until you call on your side for a truce and a
parley. We will bear no weapons against you, but we leave you to your gold. You
may eat that if you will." With that, the messengers departed swiftly, and the
dwarves were left to consider their case. So grim had Thoren become that
even if they had wished, the others would not have dared to find fault with
him. But indeed most of them seemed to share his mind, except perhaps old fat
Bomber and Feelely and Killy Bilbo, of course, disapproved of the whole turn of
affairs. He had by now had more than enough of the mountain, and being
besieged inside it was not at all to his taste. The whole place still stinks of
dragon, he grumbled to himself. And it makes me sick, and Cram is beginning
simply to stick in my throat. Chapter